Scientific Concept Extraction Pipeline Integration

Building a Scientific Concept Extraction Pipeline with SciBERT, SciSpaCy, and YAKE
Introduction
Extracting key scientific concepts from research papers requires combining multiple NLP techniques to maximize coverage and accuracy. We propose an integrated pipeline using SciBERT embeddings with KeyBERT for semantic keyphrase extraction, SciSpaCy for domain-specific named entity recognition (NER) and linking, and YAKE for statistical keyword extraction. By fusing these approaches, the pipeline can capture both the central topics and finer-grained entities in physics/AI papers, significantly increasing the number of concepts extracted per document (from ~7 in a baseline to on the order of 30–40 for a rich paper). Below, we detail best practices for integrating each component, merging their outputs with normalized confidence scores, and retrofitting these improvements into an existing pipeline (e.g. the TORI pipeline.py). Implementation guidance (installation, API usage, and design tips) is provided for each step.
SciBERT + KeyBERT for Scientific Keyphrases
SciBERT is a BERT-based language model pretrained on 1.14M scientific papers (full text, not just abstracts)
github.com
. It uses a vocabulary (scivocab) tailored to scientific terminology and achieves state-of-the-art performance on many scientific NLP tasks
github.com
. Leveraging SciBERT in a keyword extractor allows us to better identify domain-specific keyphrases. KeyBERT is a popular unsupervised method that uses BERT embeddings to find terms most similar to the document’s content
arxiv.org
. It works by encoding the entire document and candidate n-gram phrases, then ranking phrases by cosine similarity to the document embedding
arxiv.org
. By using SciBERT as the embedding model inside KeyBERT, we ensure the embeddings are tuned to scientific language, which improves the relevance of extracted keyphrases in physics and AI papers
arxiv.org
. Installation and Setup: Install the required libraries: pip install keybert transformers sentence-transformers (KeyBERT uses HuggingFace or SentenceTransformers under the hood). SciBERT is available on HuggingFace, so no special install is needed beyond transformers. You can load SciBERT in KeyBERT in two ways: (1) via the HuggingFace pipeline API or (2) via SentenceTransformers. For example:
python
Copy
Edit
from keybert import KeyBERT
from transformers import pipeline
# Load SciBERT model and tokenizer from HuggingFace
hf_model = pipeline("feature-extraction", model="allenai/scibert_scivocab_uncased")
kw_model = KeyBERT(model=hf_model)
This initializes KeyBERT with SciBERT as the embedding backend (using the uncased SciBERT model)
maartengr.github.io
github.com
. Internally, the pipeline will produce SciBERT embeddings for the document and candidate phrases, and KeyBERT will compute cosine similarities to rank the phrases. Alternatively, you could use SentenceTransformers:
python
Copy
Edit
from sentence_transformers import SentenceTransformer
kw_model = KeyBERT(model=SentenceTransformer("allenai/scibert_scivocab_uncased"))
SentenceTransformers will handle pooling of SciBERT embeddings into sentence/document vectors automatically. In either case, SciBERT’s domain knowledge should boost extraction of scientific terms (e.g. “neural network”, “quantum entanglement”) that a generic BERT might miss or mis-rank. Using KeyBERT for Extraction: Once kw_model is initialized, use kw_model.extract_keywords(doc_text, ...) to get keyphrases. You can specify keyphrase_ngram_range=(1,3) (for example) to consider unigrams, bigrams, and trigrams as candidates. It’s often useful to allow multi-word phrases since scientific concepts are frequently multi-word (e.g. “convolutional neural network”). Also consider disabling default stop_words filtering or using a domain-specific stop word list, as general stop words might remove terms like “experiment” or “data” that could be meaningful in context. For example:
python
Copy
Edit
keywords = kw_model.extract_keywords(doc_text, keyphrase_ngram_range=(1,3), stop_words=None, top_n=15)
This returns a list of tuples (phrase, score) where score is the cosine similarity of that phrase embedding to the document embedding. A higher score (closer to 1.0) means the phrase is more central to the document’s content
arxiv.org
. By default KeyBERT may return very similar terms (e.g. the singular and plural form of a word) in the top results, so it’s recommended to use diversification strategies provided by KeyBERT. Two options are Max Sum Distance and Maximal Marginal Relevance (MMR), which reduce redundancy in the keyword list
maartengr.github.io
. For instance, setting use_maxsum=True or use_mmr=True in extract_keywords can yield a more diverse set of keyphrases by balancing relevance and diversity
maartengr.github.io
. This is helpful when aiming for 30+ concepts — it prevents the list from being dominated by slight variations of the same concept. Summary: Using SciBERT with KeyBERT ensures we extract semantic keyphrases highly representative of the paper. SciBERT’s specialized embeddings capture scientific context (e.g. distinguishing “GAN” as “Generative Adversarial Network” in AI context), and KeyBERT provides a straightforward API for getting ranked keyphrases without additional training
arxiv.org
. This component will typically return each keyphrase with a confidence score (cosine similarity), which we will later normalize and fuse with other sources.
SciSpaCy for Multi-Grain NER and Entity Linking
While KeyBERT finds broad topical phrases, SciSpaCy focuses on identifying named entities and domain-specific terms in text. SciSpaCy is a SpaCy extension with models for scientific and biomedical text
allenai.github.io
. It includes a custom tokenizer for scientific text, specialized NER models, and an entity linker to map text spans to entries in scientific knowledge bases
allenai.github.io
stackoverflow.com
. This is crucial for capturing fine-grained concepts like chemical names, organism names, algorithm names, dataset names, etc., which KeyBERT might not rank highly if they are mentioned only briefly. SciSpaCy can also recognize abbreviations and link them to their expanded forms (e.g. “CNN” → “convolutional neural network”), providing multi-granularity concept coverage. Installation: Install SciSpaCy and an appropriate model. For example: pip install scispacy and then install a model package, such as the medium scientific model: pip install https://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/ai2-s2-scispacy/releases/v0.5.0/en_core_sci_md-0.5.0.tar.gz (the exact URL can be found in SciSpaCy’s documentation)
allenai.github.io
. For maximum accuracy, SciSpaCy offers a model integrating SciBERT: en_core_sci_scibert (which uses SciBERT as the transformer within spaCy)
allenai.github.io
. This model has a large vocabulary (~785k) and may yield better recognition of complex terms at the cost of speed. Alternatively, en_core_sci_sm is a faster lightweight model if performance is a concern
allenai.github.io
. NER Pipeline Usage: After loading the model (nlp = spacy.load("en_core_sci_scibert") for example), you can process a document: doc = nlp(doc_text). The SciSpaCy NER/mention-detection component will identify spans of text as entities (accessible via doc.ents). Unlike conventional NER that assigns specific labels (PERSON, LOCATION, etc.), SciSpaCy’s default models treat all detected spans as generic “ENTITIES” because they are geared toward linking to a knowledge base rather than categorizing by type
allenai.github.io
. For instance, in a biomedical text, SciSpaCy might extract entities like “Myeloid derived suppressor cells”, “immunosuppressive activity”, “hepatocellular carcinoma”, etc., covering a broad range of noun phrases (and even some verbs/adjectives if they appear as part of named concepts)
allenai.github.io
. In a physics or AI paper, SciSpaCy could detect algorithm names, technical terms, or proper nouns of experiments. This mention detector is high-recall: it will flag many possible concepts, including multi-word terms and abbreviations. To improve the quality of SciSpaCy’s output for our purposes, a few best practices are recommended:
Abbreviation Resolution: Add SciSpaCy’s abbreviation detector component: nlp.add_pipe("abbreviation_detector") before the NER pipeline. This will identify acronym definitions in the text (e.g., “Convolutional Neural Network (CNN)”) and allow the NER to treat “CNN” as an entity linked to “Convolutional Neural Network”. It sets attributes like ent._.long_form and ent._.short_form for detected abbreviations. Resolving abbreviations ensures that the short forms and long forms aren’t treated as separate concepts in the final output.
Entity Linking: SciSpaCy can map textual entities to entries in a knowledge base, assigning unique IDs and providing canonical names. This helps consolidate synonyms and variant names under a single concept. For example, “IBM” and “International Business Machines” would link to the same entity ID if a suitable KB is used. SciSpaCy supports several knowledge bases: UMLS (a comprehensive biomedical ontology), MeSH (Medical Subject Headings), GO (Gene Ontology), HPO (Human Phenotype Ontology), etc.
oyewusiwuraola.medium.com
. For general scientific text (physics/AI), UMLS is the most extensive, though it is biomedical-focused. (UMLS does contain some general scientific terms, but physics-specific ontologies might not be covered well. In absence of a physics-specific KB, UMLS is a reasonable default or one can integrate a custom KB, discussed below.) To enable linking, load the entity linker:
python
Copy
Edit
nlp.add_pipe("scispacy_linker", config={"resolve_abbreviations": True, "linker_name": "umls"})
This will download the UMLS KB data on first use (note: it’s large, ~1GB). The config resolve_abbreviations=True ensures it works with the abbreviation detector to link abbreviations to the correct concepts
stackoverflow.com
. After processing the doc, each entity span (ent) will have ent._.kb_ents, a list of candidate knowledge base entries (concept IDs) with similarity scores. Typically ent._.kb_ents[0] is the top candidate (the one SciSpaCy deems the best match). You can retrieve the canonical name via:
python
Copy
Edit
linker = nlp.get_pipe("scispacy_linker")
for ent in doc.ents:
    if ent._.kb_ents:
        kb_id, kb_score = ent._.kb_ents[0]
        concept_name = linker.kb.cui_to_entity[kb_id][1]
        print(ent.text, "→", concept_name, f"(score={kb_score:.2f})")
This maps the raw text to a standardized concept name. Using entity linking in the pipeline has two major benefits: (1) disambiguation – it reduces ambiguity by choosing which concept an entity refers to, and (2) deduplication – different surface forms referring to the same concept can be merged via their KB ID
arxiv.org
. For example, if “deep neural network” and “DNN” appear in the paper, the linker could map both to the same concept entry, preventing them from appearing as separate entries in the final concept list. (If a suitable knowledge base for physics/AI is not available, one can create a custom knowledge base and entity linker. SciSpaCy’s documentation and issues discuss how to specify custom ontologies
github.com
, though this involves preparing alias tables and might be an advanced step. In the interim, using UMLS or skipping linking might be okay for physics/CS papers, but linking to something like Wikidata or a custom list of AI concepts could significantly enhance consistency.)
Multi-grain NER: The term multi-grain here implies capturing concepts at different levels of granularity. SciSpaCy helps with this in a few ways. First, it extracts both fine-grained terms (like chemical names, specific techniques) and more general terms (like broader biomedical processes) as entities, without filtering them out
allenai.github.io
. Second, by combining multiple SciSpaCy NER models or configurations, you can get different “grains” of entities. For instance, SciSpaCy provides four NER models trained on different datasets (CRAFT, JNLPBA, BC5CDR, BIONLP13CG) each focusing on certain entity types
allenai.github.io
. In a biomedical context, combining their outputs yielded a very large set of entities: 422 unique entities from a sample corpus by using all 4 models
oyewusiwuraola.medium.com
. In our scenario, we might not have multiple domain-specific models for physics/AI, but we still achieve multi-granularity by using SciSpaCy’s broad mention detector plus linking. The mention detector grabs everything that looks like a scientific term (down to acronyms and gene names), and linking elevates those to a canonical concept level – effectively providing both the raw text span and a normalized concept. Additionally, if we identify different categories (e.g., methods, materials, metrics in AI papers), we could later tag concepts by type, but that goes beyond SciSpaCy’s current output (which doesn’t label type unless using a specific model). For now, SciSpaCy will ensure we get a high-recall list of candidate concepts from the text, complementing KeyBERT’s more precision-focused keyphrases.
Filtering: Because SciSpaCy with UMLS can be very permissive (sometimes labeling common verbs or adjectives if they appear in the KB), it’s wise to apply some filtering to its results. For example, one can filter out entities that are purely stop words or have very low linker score. If not using the linker, you might filter by part-of-speech (e.g., keep only nouns/noun phrases) to remove non-nominal entities like verbs (“assess”, “accumulate” appeared in one SciSpaCy example as an entity
allenai.github.io
). In practice, after extracting SciSpaCy entities, review a few outputs to develop rules (e.g., drop single-word entities that are <3 characters long except known abbreviations, etc.). This will increase the precision of SciSpaCy’s contribution. Summary: SciSpaCy will provide a list of named entities and terms found in the paper, each optionally linked to a canonical concept ID or name. This gives us many granular concepts (including specific ones that KeyBERT/YAKE might overlook) along with the means to unify synonyms via the linker. The output from SciSpaCy for a document is essentially an unordered set of entities (since an NER model doesn’t rank them; each may come with a linker confidence but not an “importance” score in the document). We will later assign these a confidence or weight when fusing with the other methods.
YAKE for Statistical Keyphrase Extraction
YAKE (Yet Another Keyword Extractor) is an unsupervised, domain-independent keyword extraction algorithm that relies on statistical features of the text rather than external knowledge
markovml.com
markovml.com
. It can identify salient keywords by looking at factors like term frequency, term position, context diversity, and frequency across different sentences
markovml.com
. Notably, YAKE does not require any training data or language model – it works out-of-the-box on a single document, which makes it a great complementary tool. While SciBERT+KeyBERT leverages semantic similarity and SciSpaCy uses domain knowledge, YAKE brings a purely data-driven perspective, often catching terms that stand out statistically (even if they are not central enough for KeyBERT or known to the NER model). For example, YAKE might pick up a rare term that appears multiple times or with emphasis (uppercase, in titles, etc.), which indicates it’s important in that document
markovml.com
markovml.com
. This is useful for emerging jargon or proper nouns that SciSpaCy might not recognize if they aren’t in its models, and which KeyBERT might miss if they don't significantly affect the document’s overall embedding. Installation and Usage: Install with pip install yake. The usage is straightforward – YAKE has a KeywordExtractor class. You configure it with parameters like language, maximum n-gram size, deduplication threshold (to merge similar phrases), window size, and the number of keywords to return
akashp1712.medium.com
. For example:
python
Copy
Edit
import yake
# Initialize YAKE extractor
yake_extractor = yake.KeywordExtractor(lan="en", n=3, dedupLim=0.9, dedupFunc='seqm', windowsSize=1, top=20)
# Extract keywords
keywords_yake = yake_extractor.extract_keywords(doc_text)
In this snippet, n=3 means consider up to 3-word phrases, and top=20 will return the top 20 keyphrases with their scores
akashp1712.medium.com
. YAKE’s output keywords_yake is a list of tuples (keyphrase, score). Important: In YAKE, lower scores indicate more relevant keywords
markovml.com
. The score is a composite metric where a lower value means the term is more significant according to YAKE’s features. For instance, a phrase with score 0.002 is more important than one with score 0.010. Keep this in mind for score normalization later (we’ll invert or rank these scores accordingly). It’s often beneficial to tune deduplication_threshold (dedupLim) to avoid very similar phrases. In the example above we used 0.9, which is quite high, meaning YAKE will consider two phrases as duplicates if they have ≥90% overlap. This prevents outputs like “neural network” and “neural networks” from both showing up separately. The windowsSize (context window for co-occurrence) can usually be left at default. The language is set to English (“en”), but YAKE supports multilingual extraction if needed. How YAKE Complements Other Models: YAKE is completely unsupervised and focuses on surface features, so it might extract some phrases that are not obvious semantic keyphrases but are meaningful in context (e.g., specific experiment names, compound nouns that appear frequently). It doesn’t know anything about the domain; it purely counts and scores patterns. This means it can catch unusual terms or new acronyms that SciSpaCy might not have in its models and that might not appear in SciBERT’s semantic space strongly. On the other hand, YAKE might also produce some terms that are a bit generic or not actually important (just frequently mentioned). For example, if a paper repeatedly mentions “Section” or common phrasing, YAKE could naively rank that. However, its algorithm does penalize very frequent words and common contexts to some extent (similar to IDF logic)
markovml.com
markovml.com
. Overall, YAKE adds value by improving recall of key concepts – ensuring that if something is statistically prominent in the document, it gets flagged, even if it wasn’t identified by the other methods. This can help boost the total number of extracted concepts toward the higher end of the range. Usage Example: If our document is an arXiv paper on AI, after running YAKE we might get results like [("reinforcement learning", 0.0005), ("Markov decision process", 0.0007), ("agent", 0.0012), ...] – illustrating key domain terms with scores. We will take these YAKE results and integrate them with KeyBERT and SciSpaCy results in the next step.
Merging and Normalizing Confidence Scores from Multiple Sources
With three different extraction sources (KeyBERT+SciBERT, SciSpaCy NER, and YAKE), we need to merge their outputs into a single, coherent set of concepts for each document. This involves deduplicating overlaps and normalizing confidence scores from each source into a common scale, so that we can rank or prioritize the merged list. We also need a strategy (a fusion architecture) to combine the scores or decisions from these models. Below are the steps and considerations for this fusion process:
1. Collecting and Unifying Concepts:
First, gather the raw outputs:
KeyBERT output: a list of (phrase, score) where score is cosine similarity (typically between 0 and 1). E.g., ("quantum computing", 0.62).
YAKE output: a list of (phrase, score) where a lower score means higher importance. E.g., ("quantum computing", 0.0025).
SciSpaCy output: a list of entities. If linking is used, we have pairs of (entity_text, linked_concept, link_score), otherwise just the text span. E.g., ("QC", "Quantum computing", 0.85) if “QC” was linked to the concept “Quantum computing” with 0.85 confidence. SciSpaCy might produce the same concept multiple times if it appears in text multiple times; also, one concept may have multiple surface forms (abbreviation vs full name).
We then create a unified concept candidate list. A good approach is to use the linked concept name (or ID) from SciSpaCy as the representative for SciSpaCy’s output, because that merges synonyms. For example, if SciSpaCy finds both “AI” and “artificial intelligence” and links both to the concept “Artificial Intelligence (CUI:…)", we include just one entry for that concept. Similarly, for KeyBERT and YAKE, the phrases are likely already normalized (lowercased or as in text). We should decide on a normalization for comparison: e.g., compare concepts in lowercase or ignoring punctuation. It helps to do a simple normalization like lowercase and strip punctuation for the purpose of matching duplicates, but keep the original casing for final display. Deduplication logic: We consider two extracted strings to represent the same concept if one is a case-insensitive match or substring of the other, or if SciSpaCy links them to the same KB ID. Priority can be given to longer phrases (e.g., if YAKE gives “deep neural network” and SciSpaCy gave “neural network” in a different context, we might keep the longer phrase as the canonical form). In practice:
If SciSpaCy provides a linked concept name, use that name as a key.
Map any KeyBERT/YAKE phrase that is essentially the same as a SciSpaCy concept name to that concept as well. For example, KeyBERT might output “Artificial intelligence” and SciSpaCy (via linking) yields “Artificial Intelligence”. These should be merged. Fuzzy matching or simple normalization can catch minor differences.
For overlaps between KeyBERT and YAKE: if the phrases are identical or one contains the other, treat them as one concept (the more complete phrase is preferable).
It’s useful to maintain provenance: e.g., for each concept, note which sources it came from. This can inform scoring (if a concept is found by multiple methods, we might boost its confidence).
By the end of this step, we have a set of unique concept identifiers (strings or IDs) that cover all outputs from the three methods.
2. Score Normalization:
Each method’s score ranges and meanings differ, so we convert them to a common scale (e.g., 0 to 1) for fair combining:
KeyBERT scores: These are cosine similarities. In practice, they might range from, say, 0.2 up to 0.7 or 0.8 for the top phrase, depending on the document. We can treat these as already in [0,1] (since cosine similarity is naturally bounded). If we want to be precise, we could normalize by the maximum possible or observed score: e.g., divide all KeyBERT scores by the top score in that document, so that the highest KeyBERT phrase gets a normalized score 1.0. However, since the top score may not be extremely high, another approach is to leave them as-is (0.x) but keep in mind KeyBERT rarely produces values near 1.0. For combining, it’s okay as long as we normalize others to a comparable range.
YAKE scores: Since lower is better
markovml.com
, we need to invert these. A simple method: take the worst (highest) score among the YAKE top N and the best (lowest) score, and do min-max normalization. For example, if in top 20 YAKE phrases the lowest score is 0.0005 and the highest is 0.0050, we can map 0.0005 → 1.0 and 0.0050 → 0.0, linearly. For a YAKE score s, normalized score could be score_norm = 1 - (s - s_min)/(s_max - s_min). This gives higher-is-better on [0,1]. Alternatively, rank-based normalization works: e.g., assign a score of 1.0 to the top YAKE phrase, 0.95 to the second, etc., decreasing by a fixed step or based on 1/(rank). Rank-based might be safer if the YAKE scores themselves have a skew. In summary, after normalization, a phrase that YAKE ranked #1 will have a score near 1.0, and lower-ranked ones progressively less.
SciSpaCy scores: SciSpaCy by itself doesn’t provide an “importance” score for an entity in the document. If using the entity linker, we do get a similarity score for how confident the linker is that the entity text matches a KB concept. But that is not a measure of how important that concept is in the document – it's just a matching confidence. For our purpose, we might assign a base score to SciSpaCy entities in one of two ways:
Binary or frequency-based scoring: Simply treat each unique concept from SciSpaCy as 1 (found) and 0 (not found). Or even use a small range like if the concept appears multiple times, we could scale it (e.g., a concept mentioned 5 times might be considered more important than one mentioned once). Frequency in the document can be a proxy for importance, which YAKE inherently uses and KeyBERT indirectly uses via embedding. SciSpaCy does not inherently incorporate frequency, so we can calculate it: count occurrences of each entity (or concept) in the text. We could then set SciSpaCy concept score = min(1.0, 0.1 * frequency) or some heuristic – basically more mentions yields higher score up to a cap.
Using linker confidence: If linking is enabled, we might multiply a base importance by the link confidence. For instance, we give every SciSpaCy-identified concept a base score of 0.8 (some default medium-high confidence, since if SciSpaCy detected it, it's presumably a noteworthy term), then multiply by the linker’s score. If a concept wasn’t linked or link confidence is low, we might downgrade it. However, if a concept isn’t in the KB at all, it might actually be a novel term (which could still be important), so we shouldn’t penalize it too much; perhaps in that case, rely on frequency only.
In practice, a straightforward way is: assign all SciSpaCy-extracted concepts a default normalized confidence (e.g., 0.5) and then boost it if frequency is high. Because SciSpaCy’s role is primarily recall, we usually want to include those terms but not necessarily rank them above KeyBERT/YAKE results unless they also appear frequently or were also picked up by the other methods.
After normalization, we have three scores for a concept (some might be zero if that concept wasn’t identified by a particular method). For example, concept “quantum computing” might have: KeyBERT=0.62 (raw, ~0.9 normalized if 0.62 was top), YAKE=0.93 normalized (since YAKE ranked it high), SciSpaCy=0.5 (default). Another concept “Quantum Electrodynamics” might only appear once and SciSpaCy caught it (score 0.5), YAKE gave it a moderate rank (0.4 normalized), and KeyBERT might not have it (0).
3. Score Fusion Architecture:
To fuse these scores into one final confidence or ranking, there are several strategies:
Weighted Linear Combination: Compute a weighted sum of the normalized scores from each source. For instance:
FinalScore(concept) = w_K * Score_KB + w_Y * Score_YAKE + w_S * Score_SciSpaCy
where Score_KB is KeyBERT’s normalized score, Score_YAKE is YAKE’s, and Score_SciSpaCy is SciSpaCy’s. The weights w_K, w_Y, w_S can be tuned. If we have no strong reason to favor one method a priori, we can start with equal weights (e.g. 1/3 each). However, we might choose to slightly favor KeyBERT and SciSpaCy for precision, since YAKE can occasionally introduce off-target terms. For example, w_K = w_S = 0.4 and w_Y = 0.2 is a possible weighting scheme giving a bit more influence to the semantic and NER outputs. This is a heuristic – ideally, if a labeled set of important concepts existed, one could train these weights (or even a small classifier) to optimize precision/recall. In absence of training data, equal or heuristic weights based on perceived reliability is acceptable. All combined scores would then be on a 0–1 scale (assuming weights sum to 1).
Max or Voting Fusion: Another simple approach is to not average but take the maximum score among the sources for each concept. The intuition is that if any one method is very confident this is a key concept, we treat it as such. For example, if KeyBERT gives “Bayesian Network” a 0.9 (very high) while YAKE gave it a lower rank (0.2 normalized), the max would be 0.9, reflecting that it’s likely important (KeyBERT saw it as central). Conversely, if a term only appears via SciSpaCy with a moderate default score, its max will just be that moderate score. Max fusion can work when each method’s scores are calibrated similarly. However, here a KeyBERT 0.6 and a YAKE 0.6 don’t mean exactly the same thing, so pure max might overweight SciSpaCy’s binary presence. A refinement is max of certain pairs or a conditional: e.g., if SciSpaCy and YAKE both identify something, even if each gave medium confidence, together that concept is probably important. This leads to…
Heuristic Boosts: Increase the final score if multiple methods agree. For instance, if a concept is identified by all three sources, that’s a strong signal of importance – one could add a bonus (say +0.1) to the final score (capping at 1.0). Or simply, as you aggregate, you might compute: FinalScore = (Score_KB^2 + Score_YAKE^2 + Score_SciSpaCy^2)^(1/2) (geometric combination), which inherently increases when multiple nonzero scores contribute. A simpler scheme: if concept has >1 source, multiply final score by a factor (e.g., 1.1 for two sources, 1.2 for three sources). These are arbitrary but can be tuned manually to fit expected outcomes.
Rank Fusion: Instead of combining numeric scores, you can combine rank positions from each list. Methods like Borda count or Reciprocal Rank Fusion (RRF) are used in information retrieval to merge ranked lists. For example, RRF might assign a combined score = ∑ (1 / (k + rank_i)), where rank_i is the rank of the concept in method i’s output and k is a constant (like 60) to dampen large rank values. This way, a concept that is ranked #2 by KeyBERT and #5 by YAKE would get a higher combined score than one ranked #10 by any single method. Such approaches are robust even if the raw scores aren’t comparable. If implementing rank fusion is easier, it could be a good alternative. However, since we do have scores and we can normalize them, a weighted sum is straightforward.
Regardless of the combination method, the result will be a single score per concept. We then sort the concepts by this final score in descending order. This ranked list can be the final output of extractConceptsFromDocument(). It’s wise to also output or log which methods contributed and their individual scores for transparency/debugging, though the pipeline’s consumer might only need the final list. Example: Suppose for a given paper, the concept “Transformer model” was found by KeyBERT with score 0.55, by SciSpaCy (linked to “Transformer (Machine Learning Model)”) with frequency 3 (we assign 0.6), and YAKE did not list it (score 0). If we weight equally, FinalScore = (0.83 + 0 + 0.6)/3 = 0.48 (if 0.55 was normalized to 0.83 relative to a 0.66 top). Another concept “Gradient descent” was only found by KeyBERT (0.50) and YAKE (ranked 10th, normalized 0.5), SciSpaCy missed it. FinalScore ~ (0.75 + 0.5 + 0)/3 = ~0.42. Meanwhile, a term “CIFAR-10” (dataset name) might be found by SciSpaCy (as is, or via linker to a concept) and YAKE (due to frequency), but not by KeyBERT (maybe because it’s not semantically central). If SciSpaCy default 0.5 and YAKE 0.7, FinalScore ~0.4. We see that “Transformer model” comes out on top among these by combined score. This illustrates how combining multiple signals ensures multi-faceted concepts are included, but those identified by all or by high confidence in one will rank highest.
4. Post-processing and Thresholding:
After fusion, we might impose a cutoff or limit on the number of concepts to output. If the pipeline aims for 30–40 concepts, one could take the top N (e.g., top 30) concepts by final score. Alternatively, include all concepts above a certain confidence threshold. It’s also important to double-check that the final list is not dominated by very similar concepts; if our deduplication missed any, now is a last chance to remove near-duplicates. If using linking, duplicates should already be minimized. Another good practice is to group or tag concepts by origin or type for downstream use. For example, you could label each concept in the final output with whether it came from NER, from keyphrase extraction, or both. This might be useful if later you decide to present them differently or filter (maybe the user of the pipeline wants only named entities vs keyphrases in some contexts). In summary, the fusion architecture combines the strengths of each method: KeyBERT’s semantic relevance scoring, YAKE’s statistical emphasis, and SciSpaCy’s domain entity coverage. By normalizing their confidence outputs and using a weighted combination
markovml.com
, we create a balanced ranking of concepts. Concepts identified by multiple methods naturally rise to the top, aligning with ensemble intuition that consensus implies importance. Those flagged by only one method are still present, ensuring recall, but may be ranked lower if their scores are modest. This scoring fusion approach should yield a comprehensive yet prioritized concept list for each document.
Integration into the Existing Pipeline (TORI’s pipeline.py)
Retrofitting these components into an existing pipeline involves setting up the models once, then using them in the document processing flow. Here’s how you can integrate the pieces: 1. Install Dependencies: Ensure the runtime has all required packages: keybert, transformers (for SciBERT), scispacy + a SciSpaCy model, and yake. For example, you might add to your project’s requirements or Dockerfile:
bash
Copy
Edit
pip install keybert transformers scispacy yake spacy
pip install https://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/ai2-s2-scispacy/releases/v0.5.0/en_core_sci_scibert-0.5.0.tar.gz
(The second line installs the SciSpaCy model; adjust version as needed.) If the pipeline was previously using simpler methods (like just TF-IDF or RAKE), these new dependencies will need to be included. 2. Initialize Models at Startup: It’s crucial to load large models only once and reuse them for all documents, to avoid re-loading overhead for each paper. In pipeline.py, perhaps in a setup section or globally, initialize:
The SciSpaCy NLP pipeline:
python
Copy
Edit
import spacy
import scispacy
nlp = spacy.load("en_core_sci_scibert")  # or "en_core_sci_sm" depending on preference
nlp.add_pipe("abbreviation_detector")
nlp.add_pipe("scispacy_linker", config={"resolve_abbreviations": True, "linker_name": "umls"})
This sets up the NLP pipeline with abbreviation resolution and UMLS linker
stackoverflow.com
. The first call will download necessary data (which might take a few minutes for the UMLS linker). If UMLS download is a concern in production, you can do it ahead of time or cache the data directory. Also, if memory is an issue, and if linking is not absolutely required for initial deployment, you could skip the linker to save resources, using SciSpaCy purely for mention detection. This is a trade-off between concept normalization and performance.
The KeyBERT model with SciBERT:
python
Copy
Edit
from keybert import KeyBERT
from transformers import pipeline
hf_model = pipeline("feature-extraction", model="allenai/scibert_scivocab_uncased")
kw_model = KeyBERT(model=hf_model)
# Alternatively: from sentence_transformers import SentenceTransformer; kw_model = KeyBERT(SentenceTransformer(...))
This might download SciBERT weights (around 420 MB) on the first run. Ensure the environment has enough memory. Using the uncased SciBERT is usually fine (scientific text often isn’t case-sensitive, and SciBERT uncased was recommended by the authors
github.com
). If the pipeline runs on GPU, you could consider sending the SciBERT model to CUDA for faster embedding extraction; however, since we do document and phrase encoding which isn’t huge, CPU is typically okay.
The YAKE extractor:
python
Copy
Edit
import yake
yake_extractor = yake.KeywordExtractor(lan="en", n=3, dedupLim=0.9, top=20)
Adjust parameters as needed. You could also choose top larger (say 30) if aiming for more candidates – some might be filtered out or merged later anyway. YAKE is lightweight and fast.
It might be convenient to wrap these initializations in a class or in the pipeline’s global scope. For example, define a ConceptExtractor class that loads everything in its __init__, and has a method extract_concepts(doc_text). 3. Implement extractConceptsFromDocument(doc_text): In this function (or equivalent), use the pre-loaded models to get results:
SciSpaCy NER: doc = nlp(doc_text). Then iterate doc.ents. For each, get the linked concept name if available (as shown earlier). Build a set or dict of concepts from this. For example:
python
Copy
Edit
concepts_scispacy = {}
for ent in doc.ents:
    # Use linked name if exists, else raw text
    if ent._.kb_ents:
        kb_id, score = ent._.kb_ents[0]
        name = linker.kb.cui_to_entity[kb_id][1]
    else:
        name = ent.text
        score = 1.0  # treat as confident if no linking
    name = name.strip()
    # Use a normalized key to avoid duplicates (lowercased key)
    norm_key = name.lower()
    # We may keep the highest linker score if the same concept appears again
    prev_score = concepts_scispacy.get(norm_key, (None,0))[1]
    if score > prev_score:
        concepts_scispacy[norm_key] = (name, score)
This will give a dict mapping e.g. "quantum computing" -> ("Quantum computing", 0.95). We might later use the score here as the linker confidence. We should also capture frequency: perhaps maintain another dict for concept_frequency and increment for each occurrence (even if linking yields same norm_key). After this, concepts_scispacy contains unique concepts from NER. If abbreviation detector was used, we’ll get the long forms in many cases. (You might still have separate entries for short and long forms if linking didn’t merge them, but SciSpaCy’s resolve_abbreviations=True in linker should unify them such that only the long form ends up with a KB entry typically.)
KeyBERT: keywords = kw_model.extract_keywords(doc_text, keyphrase_ngram_range=(1,3), stop_words=None, top_n=20, use_mmr=True) (for instance). This returns a list of tuples. We can convert that to a dict for easy lookup, e.g., concepts_keybert = {phrase.lower(): score for phrase, score in keywords}. We might want to store the original phrase casing as well (perhaps keep a separate map for display names).
YAKE: keywords_yake = yake_extractor.extract_keywords(doc_text). This gives list of tuples (phrase, score). Convert to dict: concepts_yake = {phrase.lower(): score for phrase, score in keywords_yake}.
Merge Keys: Now take a union of all concept keys from the three sources. For each unique concept (normalized key), gather scores from each source if present. For SciSpaCy, use perhaps the average link confidence or a default as discussed. For YAKE, invert the score (we can do the min-max normalization across that list here). For KeyBERT, we already have the cosine similarity. Then apply the chosen fusion formula. For example:
python
Copy
Edit
merged_concepts = []
for norm_key in set(list(concepts_scispacy.keys()) + list(concepts_keybert.keys()) + list(concepts_yake.keys())):
    name = None
    scores = []
    # SciSpaCy contribution
    if norm_key in concepts_scispacy:
        name = concepts_scispacy[norm_key][0]  # use nicely cased name from SciSpaCy if available
        linker_conf = concepts_scispacy[norm_key][1]
        # importance score: e.g., base 0.5 + 0.5*(min(freq/5,1)) 
        freq = doc_text.lower().count(norm_key)  # or track during NER loop
        sci_score = 0.5 + 0.5 * min(freq/5, 1.0)
        sci_score *= linker_conf  # weigh by link confidence if desired
    else:
        sci_score = 0.0
    # KeyBERT contribution
    if norm_key in concepts_keybert:
        name = name or concepts_keybert_name_lookup.get(norm_key, None) or norm_key  # get original phrase
        kb_score = concepts_keybert[norm_key]  # already 0-1
    else:
        kb_score = 0.0
    # YAKE contribution
    if norm_key in concepts_yake:
        name = name or norm_key
        yake_raw = concepts_yake[norm_key]
        # normalize YAKE raw score:
        yake_score = (yake_max - yake_raw) / (yake_max - yake_min + 1e-9)
    else:
        yake_score = 0.0
    # Final fusion (e.g., weighted sum)
    final_score = (0.4 * kb_score) + (0.4 * sci_score) + (0.2 * yake_score)
    merged_concepts.append((name or norm_key, final_score))
# sort by final_score
merged_concepts.sort(key=lambda x: x[1], reverse=True)
The above pseudocode illustrates one way: it uses a weight of 0.4 for SciSpaCy and KeyBERT each, 0.2 for YAKE. It also computes a SciSpaCy score using frequency and link confidence. The name chosen is whichever source had a proper casing or canonical form (favor SciSpaCy’s linked name if available, otherwise KeyBERT’s original phrase casing, etc.).
Truncate or filter: Take the top 30 or so concepts from merged_concepts. Optionally, remove any with very low final score to avoid noise. If needed, ensure each concept has a reasonable representation (e.g., capitalize if it’s an acronym or proper noun as per original text).
4. Output Format: The final output can be a list of concept strings or a list of objects containing concept and score. It might be wise to include the score and perhaps source info for future evaluation. For example: return [{"concept": name, "score": round(final_score,3), "sources": ["SciSpaCy","KeyBERT"]}, ...]. If the rest of the pipeline or downstream components (like a database or UI) expects just a list of concept terms, then you can provide that, but keeping the score allows later tuning or cutoff adjustments. 5. Integrate into TORI Pipeline: In the context of TORI’s pipeline.py, find where extractConceptsFromDocument is called or where concept extraction occurs. Replace or augment that with the new implementation. Ensure that the pipeline passes the raw document text to this function. After extraction, the subsequent steps (maybe storing in a database, or linking to other modules) should continue to work, ideally with minimal changes. Since we’re increasing the number of concepts, consider if any downstream component assumes a small fixed number – that might need adjusting (for instance, if they assumed <10 concepts for display, they might need to handle more now). 6. Performance Considerations: This new pipeline is heavier. SciSpaCy with a transformer, SciBERT embeddings, and YAKE calculations will take longer than a simple RAKE or TF-IDF. It’s still quite feasible per document (likely on the order of a couple of seconds per paper on CPU). You can profile the breakdown:
SciSpaCy: the slowest if using SciBERT model, because it processes each token through SciBERT. Using en_core_sci_sm (no transformer, just word vectors) would be faster but possibly slightly less recall. If performance is an issue, one strategy is to use SciSpaCy small model to get quick entities and SciBERT solely in KeyBERT. Alternatively, process only certain parts of the paper (like maybe ignore references or large appendix text if not needed for concepts).
SciBERT (for KeyBERT): computing document embedding and candidate embeddings is usually fast (the limiting factor is length of doc – you might truncate extremely long docs or break into sections for KeyBERT).
YAKE: very fast (mostly splitting text and counting).
If needed, you could run some parts in parallel (though heavy models like SciBERT might saturate CPU anyway). A simpler approach is sequential as above.
7. Testing: After integration, run the pipeline on a few known papers. Manually inspect the output concepts. You should observe a much richer list. For example, where previously the pipeline might have output ~7 broad terms, now you might see dozens: including specific entities (from SciSpaCy), general topics (from KeyBERT), and possibly additional phrases (from YAKE). Check for any obvious irrelevant entries and adjust filtering if needed (e.g., if you see a verb or a very generic word sneaking in, update the filtering rules in SciSpaCy results). By following these integration steps, the TORI pipeline will now have an enhanced concept extraction module. It is flexible (unsupervised methods that don’t require new training) and should be maintainable (each component can be upgraded independently, e.g., using a new model in SciSpaCy or a different embedding in KeyBERT if needed).
Expected Concept Quality Gains and Conclusion
Implementing the above ensemble is expected to dramatically increase both the quantity and quality of extracted concepts from scientific documents. Instead of a handful of generic keywords, the pipeline will retrieve a diverse set of keyphrases, entities, and domain terms. We anticipate moving from ~7 concepts per paper to on the order of 30–40 meaningful concepts for a well-written paper, as the user hypothesized. This is in line with findings in other domains: for example, combining multiple NER models in biomedical text yielded hundreds of unique entities, far beyond what a single method would find
oyewusiwuraola.medium.com
. In our integrated approach:
Coverage is maximized: SciSpaCy nets the domain-specific jargon and named entities (including those not explicitly highlighted by importance in the text, ensuring nothing crucial is missed). KeyBERT with SciBERT zooms in on the core topics and themes of the paper, which tend to be more general or summarative concepts. YAKE adds any statistically significant phrases that might not have been caught by the other two (perhaps new terminology or emphasis that wasn’t obvious semantically). The overlap among these sets is leveraged as a strength – if all methods find “reinforcement learning”, it will surely be top-ranked. If only one finds “temporal difference method”, it will still appear, ensuring recall of niche concepts.
Confidence scoring is more robust: By normalizing and fusing scores, the final ranking is more meaningful than any single method’s ranking. For instance, KeyBERT alone might rank a generic term highly because it appears throughout the document (e.g., “experiment”), but SciSpaCy might reveal that the key algorithm name appears only once – now our pipeline can still include that algorithm name due to SciSpaCy’s detection, and YAKE might confirm it appears in a title or figure caption, giving it a decent combined score. The ensemble mitigates biases of each method. Essentially, we have a voting system where each model “votes” for concepts, weighted by confidence, yielding a balanced outcome.
Higher precision and less redundancy: The use of SciSpaCy’s entity linker gives a way to collapse synonyms and variants, so the concept list is cleaner (each concept ideally appears once in canonical form)
arxiv.org
. This means the 30-40 concepts are 30-40 distinct ideas, not repeats. KeyBERT’s use of MMR further ensures we don’t output many redundant phrases
maartengr.github.io
. By filtering out trivial entities (like units, very common terms) using domain knowledge, the precision of the list improves.
Improved recall of important concepts: The integration with SciBERT has been shown to boost keyphrase extraction performance in scientific text
arxiv.org
. In a research context, Memarzadeh et al. (2023) found that combining unsupervised keyphrase methods with SciBERT embeddings led to superior results on clinical notes
arxiv.org
 – an indicator that our SciBERT+KeyBERT approach is well-founded. We expect a similar gain in recall of relevant concepts for physics/AI papers, given SciBERT’s training on general scientific literature.
In concrete terms, a case study on an AI paper might illustrate the gain: A simple TF-IDF or RAKE baseline might have given concepts like ["learning", "neural network", "data"]. Our enhanced pipeline might output: ["reinforcement learning", "Markov decision process", "policy network", "state space", "Q-learning", "DeepMind Lab", "generalization performance", "baselines", "neural network", "stochastic gradient descent", "Atari", "simulation environment", ...]. This mix includes specific methods, theories, and even proper nouns (datasets, environments) that provide a rich semantic fingerprint of the document. Such a list is far more useful for downstream tasks like building a concept graph, recommending related papers, or summarizing content. Design Recommendations: As a final note, maintainability and tuning are important:
Continuously evaluate the output against domain expectations. You may tweak weights or add/remove small rules (e.g., if many low-value terms slip in, adjust thresholds).
Keep an eye on performance. If processing a batch of thousands of papers, consider toggling off the heaviest parts (maybe use SciSpaCy small model, or disable linking once you have a good concept dictionary built, etc.). There is a trade-off between completeness and speed.
When possible, gather some feedback or labeled data on what truly are the key concepts in papers, and use that to refine the pipeline (even unsupervised methods can be guided by validation data for setting weights and thresholds).
Log the contributions of each method for each concept (even if just in debug mode). This can help identify if one method is underperforming or adding noise in certain cases, so you can address it (for example, if you find YAKE consistently adds irrelevant terms for a certain type of paper, you might reduce its weight or increase deduplication).
By integrating SciBERT+KeyBERT, SciSpaCy, and YAKE, we create a robust concept extraction pipeline that exploits complementary strengths: language model semantics, knowledge base entity recognition, and statistical keyword mining. This ensemble should greatly enrich the concept sets extracted from scientific documents, laying a stronger foundation for any downstream analysis like knowledge base construction, recommendation systems, or automated summarization. The expected outcome is a jump from sparse and general keywords to a dense collection of domain-specific concepts that truly reflect the content of each paper. Ultimately, this pipeline enhancement aligns with the goal of comprehensive scientific knowledge extraction, enabling systems like TORI to better “understand” and utilize the wealth of information in research articles. The increase in concept quantity (and more importantly, quality) will be evident as the pipeline is deployed on rich scientific texts, fulfilling the target of on the order of 30+ key concepts per document and significantly improving coverage of important ideas. Sources: The implementation approach and recommendations above draw upon official documentation and studies: SciBERT’s background and usage
github.com
github.com
, KeyBERT’s methodology
arxiv.org
 and usage notes
maartengr.github.io
maartengr.github.io
, SciSpaCy’s model capabilities
allenai.github.io
allenai.github.io
 and linking configuration
stackoverflow.com
 (with multiple KB options
oyewusiwuraola.medium.com
), YAKE’s algorithmic features
markovml.com
markovml.com
 and usage patterns
akashp1712.medium.com
, as well as research demonstrating the benefits of combining such techniques in scientific NLP
arxiv.org
arxiv.org
. These provide confidence that the proposed pipeline will achieve the intended improvements in concept extraction.